<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://critchlow.us/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://critchlow.us/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2023-11-06T16:16:57+00:00</updated><id>https://critchlow.us/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Dominic Critchlow</title><subtitle>I am Dominic - Doing fun things on the internet. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">How the Pentagon could think about Software Development</title><link href="https://critchlow.us/blog/2022/how-the-pentagon-could-think-about/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How the Pentagon could think about Software Development"/><published>2022-06-29T21:01:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-06-29T21:01:00+00:00</updated><id>https://critchlow.us/blog/2022/how-the-pentagon-could-think-about</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://critchlow.us/blog/2022/how-the-pentagon-could-think-about/"><![CDATA[<figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="https://storage.googleapis.com/portfolio_images_dominic/portfolio_images/Planes-13-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="https://storage.googleapis.com/portfolio_images_dominic/portfolio_images/Planes-13-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="https://storage.googleapis.com/portfolio_images_dominic/portfolio_images/Planes-13-1400.webp"/> <img src="https://storage.googleapis.com/portfolio_images_dominic/portfolio_images/Planes-13.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <p>Deputy Secretary of Defense Dr. Hicks spoke in her announcement of the DOD AI and Data Acceleration initiative (ADA) that, “A key part of an AI-ready department is a strong data foundation.” In the <a href="https://media.defense.gov/2020/Oct/08/2002514180/-1/-1/0/DOD-DATA-STRATEGY.PDF">2020 DOD Data Strategy</a>, the department presented the DOD’s data goals through VAULTS (Visible, Accessible, Understandable, Linked, Trustworthy, Interoperable, and Secure). The key to making both of these happen is software. In this context, software is the entire range from extensive COTS tools, like Microsoft Excel, all the way to a few lines of python code an analyst writes to create a report. Currently, the Pentagon treats both ends of the Software spectrum very differently. In simple terms, data is visible, accessible, understandable, linked, trustworthy, interoperable, and secure by software regardless of the scale. The Pentagon needs to make software production as easy as writing a memo. Risk is inevitable; however, hiding behind the excuses of security is an even greater risk.</p> <ol> <li>Make all software development tools employees want available</li> <li>Empower people across any job role to build small applications with accessible interfaces</li> <li>Provide ways to release software on all networks quickly</li> </ol> <p>These ideas are not new or innovative; most of these are already implemented across the department when you go to specific agencies or commands. Again, this shows that we have the expertise to do this; however, we need to empower civilian employees and service members across the entire Department.</p> <h1 id="make-all-software-development-tools-employees-want-available">Make all software development tools employees want available</h1> <p>The key term here is <strong>“want.”</strong> Working as a software developer in any other context allows you to set up your preferred working environment. The department has several service providers that have their lists of approved software, which always seem to lack the tools you are used to working with. If you get lucky, the service provider can suggest an alternative on the approved list, a version a few years out of date that may only match part of your requirements.</p> <p>On the other hand, you may run into a scenario where your specific job role is unauthorized for using this software, or worse, it does not exist. There is currently no incentive for the service provider to improve this process.</p> <p>On the odd chance that the requested software is approved, most service providers have to install it on your specific computer, where then you have to cross your fingers that the person assigned to your ticket knows what they are doing.</p> <p>A solution that has proven to work is to host private copies of software on all of the distinct networks and mandate that all service providers allow self-installation from this hub. In addition, service providers need to reduce current restrictions on command line use, programming languages, and automated access to file systems, among others, to best facilitate this.</p> <p>This could look something like this:</p> <ul> <li>tools.dev.mil — Entire executables;</li> <li>pypi.dev.mil — Registry for Python packages;</li> <li>npm.dev.mil — Registry for Node packages;</li> <li>docker.dev.mil — Docker Image Repository;</li> </ul> <p>These are examples of domains on NIPR and should be mirrored on other networks simultaneously. A solution like this is possible because of the wide use of open-source software. Changing the language from “need” to “want” and focusing on the “want” will slowly build an entire infrastructure of valuable tools that will accelerate the production of in-house software.</p> <h1 id="empower-people-across-any-job-role-to-build-small-applications-with-accessible-interfaces">Empower people across any job role to build small applications with accessible interfaces</h1> <p>Analytics are not static products; they are dynamic and should be treated that way. Freezing analytics by writing reports and printing numbers is inevitable; however, the data and analytics do not have to be. Creating a data-centric department presents the opportunity for all employees to learn how to automate portions of their workflow. This can be done through click and drag tools or a scripting language such as python.</p> <p>Not every analyst needs or will want to write code. Still, every analyst should have access to a community of development to learn or work with developers to produce accessible products. This could look like a weekly meet-up where analysts could sit side by side with a developer and build a quick prototype of an analytic or automation or, at the same time, learn from a community presenter on how to make a Jupyter Notebook to rerun analytics needed for their day to day.</p> <p>Accessing databases from any domain has been an enormous problem in the department, mainly stemming from legacy systems that were never designed to be used by external software. By empowering people to build small accessible applications, the Department can get ahead of this problem. Starting with the premise that every application is an Application Programming Interface (API) before a web-based application removes this lockdown. This, however, introduces a new problem in the security space. The big concern is having individuals access data they should not have or tracking what information was extracted from systems. Expecting each developer or analyst to solve this problem themselves is a recipe for disaster and data leaks.</p> <p>In the same vein as self-hosting outside packages and software, the department should develop DoD-specific modules and libraries for situations like this. A standard library for Common Access Card (CAC) certificate authentication and hosting authentication services to provide short-term certificates that individuals can apply for works hand in hand with giving developers the tools they need to succeed while keeping good security controls. Such services and libraries should be developed centrally to ensure the security standards are kept up to date.</p> <p>Building a community of sharing and educating could look something like this:</p> <ul> <li>dev.mil — Hub for all DoD developers;</li> <li>stackoverflow.dev.mil — Knowledge sharing space;</li> <li>gitlab.dev.mil — DoD specific code sharing; etc.</li> </ul> <p>I am looking specifically at code sharing and the use of open-source software. The department has a congressional mandate to open source 20% of code developed internally. Therefore, when feasible, public places like GitHub and GitLab should be utilized to make code accessible even outside of the DoD. Using open-source technology comes with the understanding of giving back, which the department has failed at so far. The Defense Digital Service has already outlined an easy path to do so (<a href="https://code.mil/how-to-open-source.html">https://code.mil/how-to-open-source.html</a>). The department has even started this on GitHub; it lacks a more considerable commitment across the board (<a href="https://github.com/deptofdefense">https://github.com/deptofdefense</a>).</p> <h1 id="provide-ways-to-release-software-on-all-networks-quickly">Provide ways to release software on all networks quickly</h1> <p>The final step of any piece of software is the release. On the open internet, this is as simple as acquiring a domain name from a registrar and hosting the application on something like a virtual machine of a cloud provider. However, the DoD’s process involves an undetermined amount of steps and approvals. The process is also seemingly designed for significant pieces of software built by huge teams. It should not take lawyers, and security experts to release a web application that can be developed in a matter of hours.</p> <p>It seems feasible that every developer should have access to a personal domain to deploy an application of an overview of what they work on and then have the ability to deploy applications on subdomains from there. We can look at this as a testing ground for applications or, as the department likes to put it, a “non-authoritative” source. It should then be easy to apply for a permanent domain name to bring the application into an “authoritative” state.</p> <p>Having a domain to deploy to isn’t enough, though. Each developer needs access to virtual computing stations to deploy these applications, which must be accessible on the respective network it’s deployed on.</p> <ul> <li>myportfolio.dev.mil — Developer’s personal homepage</li> <li>sampleproject.myportfolio.dev.mil — Project in development that anybody on the network can access</li> <li>finalproject.dev.mil — The production version of a product</li> </ul> <p>and so on …</p> <h1 id="next-steps">Next Steps</h1> <p>The department should have an entire office dedicated to making software available on all networks, The Office of Software Enablers. This office should have three focus areas: tools, people, and accessibility.</p> <p>There should be no distinction between job titles for employees that want to partake in software development. The goals of this office are measured in each area by:</p> <ul> <li>Tools</li> <li>Number of requests approved and software published</li> <li>The difference in time new versions are available to be published</li> <li>Accessibility to the tools across the department</li> <li>People</li> <li>Growth of the community developers</li> <li>Software Development Hires</li> <li>Number of projects developed for Open Source</li> <li>Accessibility</li> <li>Number of sample projects converted to full production</li> <li>Time from development to publication on respective networks</li> <li>Time of acquiring domain names</li> </ul> <p>The department must take significant steps to have a strong software development focus, which sets the foundation for a data-centric department. Focusing on these three areas will kickstart a movement to put the department on track to attract talented developers that can have a tangible impact on the operations across the entire Department of Defense.</p> <p><em>This article is my own opinion and does not reflect the views of the US government or the Department of Defense.</em></p> <p>Prepublication Link: <a href="https://storage.googleapis.com/dc_public_documents/publish_documents/How%20the%20Pentagon%20could%20think%20about%20Software%20Development.pdf">https://storage.googleapis.com/dc_public_documents/publish_documents/How%20the%20Pentagon%20could%20think%20about%20Software%20Development.pdf</a></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="DoD"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[An opinion piece on Software Development at the Pentagon]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Austin Peay High Altitude Ballooning</title><link href="https://critchlow.us/blog/2017/APSU-High-Altitude-Ballooning/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Austin Peay High Altitude Ballooning"/><published>2017-08-21T12:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2017-08-21T12:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://critchlow.us/blog/2017/APSU-High-Altitude-Ballooning</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://critchlow.us/blog/2017/APSU-High-Altitude-Ballooning/"><![CDATA[<p>During the 2021 Total Solar Ecplise, four years of undergraduate research came to fruition. The Austin Peay State University’s (APSU) High Altitude Balloon Research Team hosted several Teams at the APSU Farm to launch balloons to observe the scientific effects of a Solar Ecplise. Over the four years I spent on and off working on this project, I learned an incredible amount about balloons, electronics, software, science, etc. In this post, I am documenting a few of the projects or steps that lead us to my final launch as a student.</p> <p>A good summary of such a balloon launch is this video.</p> <iframe width="100%" height="375px" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/Z30EtqZ8Pkw" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen=""></iframe> <p> </p> <p>Austin Peay’s location made it the prime location for observing the Total Solar Eclipse. People traveled from all across the world to see the Eclipse from the Austin Peay Campus.</p> <p> </p> <iframe width="100%" height="375px" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/8babWRWM4Tg" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen=""></iframe> <p> </p> <p>Over the four years, I could present progress on the balloon team’s research. We presented the work at <em>Posters On The Hill</em>, a Tennessee State Legislator event at the TN State Capitol to share Academic Research with lawmakers and the public. I presented a specific payload on Remote Sensing from a balloon. This payload flew during the Eclipse and could highlight imagery in specific wavelengths looking at the earth before, during, and after the Eclipse.</p> <p> </p> <object width="100%" height="600px" data="/assets/pdf/Poster_on_the_hill.pdf" type="application/pdf"></object> <p> </p> <p>During the final months, and as a senior research project, I worked on the way to passively stabilize the payload during flight. Unfortunately, we observed excessive turbulence and rotation during our test flights. The instability caused several experiments to provide subpar results. The poster describes the lightweight construction of the payload with multiple approaches to stabilize the payload passively.</p> <p> </p> <object width="100%" height="600px" data="/assets/pdf/AdvanLab_Poster.pdf" type="application/pdf"></object>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Academic"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Austin Peay State University Ballooning Team Solar Eclipse]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Dynamic Network Alignment</title><link href="https://critchlow.us/blog/2016/Dynamic-Network-Alignment/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Dynamic Network Alignment"/><published>2016-08-15T12:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2016-08-15T12:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://critchlow.us/blog/2016/Dynamic-Network-Alignment</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://critchlow.us/blog/2016/Dynamic-Network-Alignment/"><![CDATA[<p>I was privileged to attend the University of Notre Dame’s Data Intensive Scientific Computing Program, where I worked on Dynamic Network Alignment. At the Complex Networks (CoNe) Lab, I got to study under Prof. Tijana Milenkovic to understand the complex interactions in Social and Biological Networks. We applied Graph Theory approaches to add to the field of Network Alignment.</p> <p>We worked on our presentation skills as a final project by filming videos explaining our summer research.</p> <iframe width="100%" height="375px" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/dHbQpJsFx3g" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen=""></iframe> <p> </p> <p>Our study defines network alignment as an injective (one-to-one) mapping between the compared networks. Network alignment can only be approximated as it falls into the category of NP-hard problems. Existing (approximate) network alignment methods allow for studying only static networks. However, most real-world complex systems are dynamic. With the recent increase of temporal network data available about such dynamic systems, it only seems natural to use the time information in network alignment. Hence, we aim to generalize an existing state-of-the-art method for aligning static networks to their dynamic counterpart to allow for aligning dynamic networks.</p> <p> </p> <object width="100%" height="600px" data="/assets/pdf/ND_POSTER_Printed.pdf" type="application/pdf"></object> <p> </p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Academic"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[University of Notre Dame Data Intensive Scientific Computing Program]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">ZnO/MgO Crystaline Structure</title><link href="https://critchlow.us/blog/2015/ZnOMgO-Structure/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="ZnO/MgO Crystaline Structure"/><published>2015-08-01T12:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2015-08-01T12:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://critchlow.us/blog/2015/ZnOMgO-Structure</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://critchlow.us/blog/2015/ZnOMgO-Structure/"><![CDATA[<p>I attended Vanderbilt University in the summer of 2015, working in the Pentalides Group. I focused on a Theoretical Physics study of Magnesium Oxide deposition on Zinc Oxide Nanowires.</p> <p> </p> <object width="100%" height="600px" data="/assets/pdf/ZnOMgO-Poster.pdf" type="application/pdf"></object> <p> </p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Academic"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Vanderbilt University Research Experience for Undergraduates]]></summary></entry></feed>